so thanks everybody for for uh joining uh this
magnet seminar as i mentioned earlier it's uh
delayed but better late than than never
um and so for those who haven't um been to any
of the magnet seminars um just a quick outline of
the the presentations and you will hear
some background noise on my end this morning
so the format of these seminars is is a
presentation that's about 25 to 30 minutes
and so i kindly ask that you keep your microphone
muted during that time so that we don't disturb
the speaker and if you are having any problems
with the internet connection if you turn off
your video feed that can help to to improve things
um after the uh presentation we'll have time for
a 10-15 minute question and discussion session
and if you don't want to to ask a question um on
zoom you can type a question into the chat and i
will read it out to the uh to the speaker for you
and as you know because these are online seminars
and we've all got our life going on around us in
the background if you do have to get up and go
please just go and a lot of different things
going on so that's not a problem at all as i said
these seminars are recorded and i'll talk about
what we can access these recordings at the end
of the seminar and and at the end of end of it
all we'll have time uh for a bit of a catch-up a
bit of a social for everybody because we're all
uh at the four corners of the planet so it's a
good chance to to catch up with everybody and that
part of the seminar uh isn't actually recorded
so it's it's a fair free for all for everybody
and so um today i'm delighted um to to introduce
andrew roberts um as our speaker for today
this he is marking the start of a shift um in our
normal time scale for running the magnet seminars
so now we're going to be running on a european
uh eastern hemisphere time scale so that um our
colleagues across the world can have a chance
to to actually participate and interact in these
seminars and so today andy is going to talk about
magnetotactic bacteria and so without much to do i
will pass over to to you andy perfect okay thanks
colleagues for coming and thanks for your patience
really sorry about that um i've changed my title
a little bit and greg didn't tell me it was 25
to 30 minutes so i don't know if i'll keep to that
but but um i hope you'll find it interesting um so
i'm going to talk about mtb and magnetic fossils
and there are people in the room who know way more
than me um and and i i i hope i know that and
i think you know that so um i i offer this talk
in in that light and i see my colleague uh legion
juarez in the room as well and he's done a lot of
the work that i'm going to talk about today and
i'm going to acknowledge that in due course so
mtb if you look down a microscope and and jinhua
also gave me a lot of the graphics for this talk
too so um i acknowledge that if you look down a
microscope uh and here's the the droplet of water
and here's the field direction in this this is
what's called a magnetodrome the bacteria will
swim towards the applied field direction right
so they swim this way and then the applied field
switches direction they swim the other way
you go around in circles and they follow that
okay so we all know magnetotactic bacteria
in our community and you know this is the
classic image of a chain of magnetosomes either
of magnetite or grigoite and it's it's that long
uh chain that provides the strong anisotropy
along that chain that provides the the
bacterial cell with a compass-like needle that
enables it to to navigate along the field and
if you looked at a tem image of those uh
magnetic particles in a magnetosum chain
they're not independent of each other they're
strongly interacting but they interact
such that they're flux-linked and so you see a
large single dipole associated with that single
magnetite chain this is from electron holography
and and you know you might ask yourself well how
does that actually work uh aaresh kameli from
from uc berkeley did this beautiful study where
where these are the magnetosomes the magnetosome
is the organelle within within the cell and and
the magnetosomal magnetite or grigor resides
within that is biomineralized perfectly and
beautifully within that but the chain structure
is held together by these cytoskeletal protein
filaments which which line everything up so it's
an extremely intricate and and beautiful structure
and the the standard view of of where these
things live is that they live around oxic
anoxic transition zones or oxicanoxic interfaces
oatz or oii and the idea is that if you come from
the atmosphere down into into the water column
or sediment you'll have an oxygen gradient from
atmospheric levels to to nothing and an opposing
gradient of reduced species um probably sulfur
coming upwards uh with a negative gradient and
in between you have this transition zone between
oxidizing and reducing anoxic environments um i
have a problem with this figure at lots of levels
um i i love dennis and richard frankel i think
they're the the legends of the field but i
think this depiction is flawed in many ways
and it's it's repeated in the literature so
i'll explain why i think that's problematical but
basically the idea is that the the the bacteria
swim up and down geomagnetic field lines uh using
their flagellae and you know since i started
reading this literature 30 years ago i have all
these moments of really do they really think that
um and so in the abstract for the talk i've asked
a lot of questions i won't have time to go through
all those questions today but there's a
lot of things that make me think really
how does that really work um so then
that's where magnetotactic bacteria
live allegedly um when they die uh the idea
is that then their nano magnetic remains
um get buried in sediment and provide really
beautiful ideal magnetic recording these single
domain particles and that was put forward by
joe kirschbink who who coined the term magneto
fossils and when you look at their paper in 1984
i'm not bagging it i think it's classic work and
have cited it many times but the quality of the
imagery is is not great compared to to today
but a couple of years later you know with john
stoltz and colleagues i think joe was a co-author
of that paper they're producing beautiful images
of the type that that we're more used to um but
classic work and and the idea was that magneto
fossils are supposed to be a significant recorder
of paleomagnetic information and throughout
my paleomagnetic life i've said well really
to lots of questions so um my first question
is if magnetotactic bacteria live around an oai
won't die genesis remove them it's a redox
zonation and when you get into reducing sediments
sulphatic sediments are corrosive to magnetite
so they should dissolve so then the question
is do they always inhabit oai environments
other questions are when did they appear in
the geological record does that tell us anything
independent about the geodynamo and its evolution
when you see these these pictures of of bacteria
swimming up and down across a redox or donation
i've always wondered well why do they do that
you know why why do they choose to live there
um is that the electron transfer
through through moving through these
redox zones giving them energy for a battery
that helps them to metabolize or are they
actually involved in the biogeochemical cycling
that that that occurs across that that transition
and as a paleomagnetist so some of the questions
i've posed in the abstract are things like
relative paleo intensity if you have detrital and
biogenic particles does what does that mean for
recording efficiency and we've published a lot
of that so i'm not going to talk about it today
if you want to talk to me about that happy to
do that on offline um but but really one of the
things that that interests me a lot is can the
morphology of the magnetofossils tell us about
the environment and can we then use that if
we find magnetofossils uh can we use that as
a paleo environmental proxy so those are a bunch
of questions and i have lots of other questions
like what happens at the equator what's the
benefit of magnetic taxes at the equator you know
um all sorts of questions come up we don't
have time for a lot of these today um but but
let's have a go at some of these questions
um so some years ago when i when i decided
mtb were more interesting to the research
questions i was interested in i hooked up
with a long-term friend yongshun pan in
in beijing uh this is li jinhua who who
who i'll show another picture of and ching song
liu all great friends um and so we wrote a joint
grant together dennis basilenski was involved and
um and and yongshin brought these two characters
into the project uh waylin and and and legionwa
and um these guys are proper microbiologists so
and they've got they're clever and they've got a
lot of tools at their disposal that that really
helped to address a range of interesting questions
so uh it's been one of life's great delights for
me to work with these guys um really interesting
science and when you're bored during covert
uh there's been a lot of interesting
papers that we've been working on together
and then jinhua has a student pay you you who who
who has done some of the work that i'll talk about
today and and with way uh i have a student
pranami who's stuck in india at the moment
um where covert is raging and and she can't get
back into china to to do the dual phd between
um and she can't get to australia either so it's
pretty tough for her and of course greg thanks for
the invitation for the talk um you've changed
a bit over the years as of but um there we go
um so my view of mtb is that they're um if
you'd asked me anytime before 10 years ago
i would have said they're interesting
but not geologically important
and and the reason for that is what happens
when mud gets buried when mud gets buried
diagenesis happens and what is digenesis well
it's simply the the physical and chemical changes
uh that occur in a sediment as it converts to rock
dewatering compaction physically but chemically
in particular organic matter burial is really
critical for preservation of paleomagnetic
signals so diogenetic changes uh result from
from the microbial degradation of organic matter
and if you get into sulfitic environments
magnetite gets dissolved unprotected magnetite
gets dissolved uh and much of the paleomagnetic
and the perimagnetic signal carried by by those
unprotected magnetite particles so organic
matter burial is really important so in in
my life i would say i've become more expert in
diagnosis than i wanted to simply because i wanted
to understand what was wrecking the records and
i'd say diagenesis is ubiquitous it affects every
record sometimes it's it's subtle sometimes it's
pervasive and and our job is really to figure out
at what end of the spectrum we're operating
um so so here we go this is the standard um
die genetic zonation in sediments
and the depth is arbitrary because
this depth could be really thick uh tens hundreds
of meters thick or it could be millimeters thick
depending on organic carbon flux and so you know
you start with degrading organic matter with
oxygen and when all the oxygen is consumed then
you start to reduce the next species that that
is most readily uh usable so that's nitrate
then manganese oxides then iron oxides
than than sulfide than than methane right and so
um you get these ranges of of of diagenetic zones
and different minerals form and and dissolve
and when you get into this sulfidic realm here
magnetite dissolves it's unstable
so it's not going to be preserved
so magnetite is preserved in
this oxic to to nitrogenous
zone um and then and then gray guy produces
will occur deeper where it's self-fitting
and uh we there's not a huge amount of work here
on the grigorite producers which i think is a real
pity um i i expect them to be really common
in the geological record unlike the magnetite
producers but um that's a hard problem to work
on the particles are a ratty looking they form
poor chains they're poorly crystalline that's a
tricky problem but i think it's one that deserves
attention but anyway my view for 20 years was
that um if you're in this redox zonation and
the magnetofossils are forming here by the
time they bury here they'll be dissolved so
geologically they're not interesting magnetically
they're not important and and uh 10 in 2008 when
bob koppen and joe kershwink published this paper
you would have concluded i'm right wouldn't you
you'd say what they made a nice statement the
pre-quaternary magneto-fossil record is sparse
more magneto-fossil-bearing localities
have been identified in the quaternary
than in all the rest of earth history um
and and so up till 2008 there were very few
um maybe ten or so um pre-quaternary magnetofossil
records documented by cop and kershawing
and what we found since then um is actually
they're really common um in all the and it's not
just our group lots of groups have have done work
but we've done a lot of work in pelagic marine
carbonates they're ubiquitous in those sediments
uh various lake sediments various terrigenous
marine sediments they're really widespread as
long as the sediment hasn't become sulfatic
and and so the question is is why or why haven't
they been dissolved um and so toshi yamazaki's
done some beautiful work in the pacific ocean
in the north and south pacific this is a the
the beautiful colors here are chlorophyll so
chlorophyll is an indic this is from remote
sensing it's a beautiful indicator of surface
water productivity and productivity is limited
by various micronutrients so the plankton in
these environments have abundant nitrogen nitrate
phosphate silica but they lack iron so iron is a
limiting micronutrient and if you supply a little
bit of iron from dust or or volcanic ash you can
create a phytoplankton bloom so this area of the
north pacific is a is a is what they call hnlc
high nitrate low chlorophyll so you can see low
chlorophyll low productivity because it's iron
limited um and and what toshi finds in sediments
in these hnlc environments in the north and
south pacific is oxygen is easily measurable
throughout the sediment column right down to
basement right it's 200 micro molar here and
80 at the bottom so that's not that's not close
to an anoxic transition yeah and and you get these
beautiful equine octahedral magneto fossils all
the normal magnetic indicators of their presence
we found the same uh shadong zhang worked in our
group for a little while in xingsung's group in
sustech and if you look at pharah manganese
nodules on the sea floor in the pacific
again uh the magnetic signal in these in these
uh nodules is carried by biogenic magnetite and
several groups have discovered this almost
simultaneously um and and that's interesting
and and there's magnetic signals carried
by low resolution but but environmental
signals carried by these biogenic magnetites
in in in these nodules so i would argue that
okay we're not part of an oai here right it's
it's oxic um it might be nitrogenous in places
um but you're in the really the upper part of any
redox zonation so i'm happy to call it that there
that these organisms love redox donations but
this is not an oai it's miles above it um so
what's what's the explanation well this is the
basic poor water profile that i showed you before
with arbitrary depths and then if you put real
depths on them in different environments this is a
high productivity region in the equatorial pacific
from john tardino's work and and with poor waters
measured and you can see that sulphide kicks
in at 10 meters so you get a beautiful magneto
fossil record for about 10 meters and then it gets
dissolved uh north atlantic ocean drift deposits
is still in in these zones where magnetofossils
will be preserved until about 80 meters
so you get beautiful records in those sediments
and in the north and south pacific oxygen
penetrates basically to to the basalt basement and
so you're in different parts of this this redox
donation and here you're basically staying up here
for the whole thickness of the sediment column
and here you get there within 10 meters okay so so
that's my view of of what's happening um so to try
and understand this better where else would you
go but vegas so uh dave and i uh went to to vegas
my secretary at the time time got really excited
about putting us in the bellagio where we had a
enjoyable time my ex-wife julia roberts tagged
along for the trip um and we went to visit dennis
and i got him chatting about about uh you know
what are the is the oai concept really valid
and it took him back to this paper that he
co-authored with with blakemore back in 1985
and they make this statement in it and they used
the word microaerobic right optimum cell magnetism
occurred under microaerobic conditions for us
geophysicists that means ten to the minus six
for microbiologists i learned that day it means
anything less than atmospheric yeah so in this
case what they measured was one twentieth to
one fortieth of atmospheric but it was not
uh anoxic yeah and so there's there's plenty of
back mtb species as far as my understanding and
there's experts in the room who could argue with
it but as far as my understanding goes they're
quite happy in those environments it's less
oxygen than than the atmosphere of course um but
but they're still happy in in those sorts of
environments and so when we talk about oais
it might some people might consider this
semantics but it's important for preservation
and and happy to talk about redox gradients but i
think we're miles above an oai when we're getting
stuff preserved in the geological record this is
a nice figure from from the munich group and they
show it very very well where you know you've
got this oxygen level in the water column and
then the sediment the oxygen level drops off
obviously and the mtb are still still fairly
happy at almost atmospheric levels but clearly
they they're happier when the oxygen levels drop
off uh i don't know how low that is but anyway
that there's an environment that's miles above uh
uh reducing uh selfittic um where these guys are
happy okay so what are the what are the bacteria
doing there and for how long have they been doing
it and this is where i i get to pump up the tires
of jinhua a little bit because i think the
work that he's been doing is just stunning
um and and the problem when we come to do this
sort of work is that there are really very few
species that are cultured in the lab only three or
four or five i don't know how many but it's small
so to to make progress we need to work with
dirty environmental samples and then you've got
hundreds thousands of species in the same in the
same sample so how do you handle them um and so
jinhua's come up with a workflow that that i think
is magic um it combines fluorescence microscopy
um hybridization with these with these probes and
sem and tem imaging sem imaging these days with
field emission systems is really really very good
but of course the tem images are so much better
um but the four steps of this are to enrich um
in your microcosm the the mtb cells from from the
environmental sample then you do gene sequencing
of them uh then you do this fluorescence
uh in-situ hybridization analysis um which
enables you to tag these with different
markers so that you can see which species are
the same which strains are the same and then
and then you you you can image them and
then characterize the magnetic particles
and and so you can do the whole thing you you
get the phylogeny you you get the morphology of
the cell and the number of particles and the the
configuration single spread strand double spring
quadruple strand chain bundles whatever
non-chained and and then you get the the um
the morphology okay so the the the steps that that
that are taken is that you go to your environment
wherever it might be swamps coastal environments
lakes deep sea um and you've got this complexly
mixed sample with all of these different types
of bacteria you you do the phylogenetics to to
to understand you know where these guys fit in in
in the scheme of life um and then you characterize
and so you know the morphology and the composition
we use transmission electron micro microscopy
scanning transmission electron micro microscopy
synchrotron stuff nano sims etc and you get a
holistic view of of what's going on and i think
genvar and and colleagues do a really stunning job
of this and so then in terms of interpretation
you've got the ecology you've identified
the species um then you can understand the
biomineralization measure the magnetic properties
and so to go from from these two-dimensional
images of morpholi of morphology of course
that's a cross-section the electron beams
transmitting through those particles and what
you're trying to do is to understand the shape
of the particles so they tilt the stage through
many many angles to get a tomographic image to
build these 3d crystal structures of of the the
the magnetite particles and then um based on on
this kind of stuff you can start to to think about
interpreting magnetofossil records um most
of what we see as as polymagnetists is this
and i'm very interested that we we come to an
understanding of this in the modern so that we
can constrain this in the ancient um and it's
it's turning out this is incredibly complicated
and it's going to take a long time to work out
but i i think it's fundamental and has to be done
okay so so what we're finding is that the the
phylogeny is incredibly diverse multiple phyla
you see single-stranded guys
you see double stranded you see
double double stranded you see you know
chains at angles you see chain bundles you
see these watermelon things with multiple chain
bundles the diversity is incredible in terms of
the the type of bacteria the cocky versus the the
mtb that the the types of particles they produce
the inclusions you can see there are inclusions
within these of different types and and that's
all playing into this incredible phylogenetic
diversity so you know if you went uh before 2012
it was thought that there were two filer in
which mtb originated then between 2012 and 2015
three then 2015 to 2020 five and just last
year it's ballooned and um uh i mean every time
these guys go and look down their microscopes and
do the phylogenetics they're finding new species
and and the phylogeny is ex the diversity of the
phylogeny is expanding incredibly um so so one of
the problems in this that i've started to read
about and i find really interesting is there's
a thing called horizontal gene transfer so you
know most of us i think are probably used to
thinking about biology in these terms as a tree
of life where there's vertical inheritance of dna
and evolution happens vertically uh starting
with the the the last universal common ancestor
um but what horror horizontal gene transfer
says is that particularly prokaryotes
can transfer genetic information horizontally so
unrelated organisms can transfer genetic material
um through this hgt mechanism so really it makes
understanding of evolution messy and and then if
if that's happening you could say well how do we
know the reality but there are there are rules
that they put around this and all of the work
that's being done around this meets those rules
um so it's leading to a more complex view of of
evolution and in these these things so i'm curious
to see how that evolves but um okay what do i know
i'm i'm i'm a paleomagnetist but i'm inclined to
think it's real for lots of reasons that i'll i'll
talk about soon so then then the question is when
did mtb evolve and jinhua gave me this image i'm
not sure where it's from they were anyway um but
you know we're used to seeing magnetofossils in
the cenozoic and in the polysenior scene thermal
maximum 56 million years ago there's lots of
them and and most records have lots of them
and then in the cretaceous in southern england
in chalks they're abundant and in the deep ocean
they're abundant then go back in time there's a
lot of controversy around the gunflink gunflint
shirt probably people in the room are working on
that and and they consider it putative that the
evidence is controversial um and then of course
there's the martian meteorite the allen hills
meteorite that that has a date of three point nine
to four billion years and the argument is that
uh martian magneto fossils hitched a ride on a
meteorite and and um and seeded mdb on earth um so
wayland did a really beautiful study greg was
a co-author on this a few years ago i i wasn't
but they used bayesian molecular clock dating
and found that the magnetosome gene clusters
these are the things that that are responsible
for for biomineralization and chain arrangement
within magnetosomes originated before or near
the divergence between the nitrospurate and
the proteobacteria that means that was in the
archaean right and and that is before the great
oxidation event so we're used to thinking of
bacteria in the modern where we have oxygen in
the atmosphere but now if we're pushed into the
archaean very little oxygen in the atmosphere
and then what's the advantage of having
magnetotaxes if there's no geomagnetic field
so it's suggesting an antiquity of the field and
providing an independent line of evidence that's
very exciting about understanding the geodynamo so
i think that's very cool and so we we've got a job
to do to to really trace that in the magnetofossil
record which i think is very exciting
then the question is well were they were they
living across an oai in a world where there's
where there's no oh um and some people
have come up with evidence that there were
you know um oais in this in the shallow
ocean in in that world but it's controversial
and so we don't know clearly it was some
sort of redox gradient uh so that's the way
i prefer to think about that their habitats
rather than than than in that way then
you know this nanotomography of tilting the
tem stage and and imaging and then putting
through a crystal model to to come up with the the
details of the geometry of the particles produces
these very beautiful images of of the diversity of
not only the bacteria and the chain arrangements
and all the rest but of the the magnetosomal
magnetite as well so you know by this really
detailed work on on individual particles and
and getting the nanotomography even you know
going down to the atomic level and then picking
out the the details of the crystallography of of
the individual crystals then we can tie that
to the phylogenetics and and here the colors
correspond to five different phyla okay and i'm
just keeping it that way so that you can see
that you know the bacteria themselves are
diverse the chain arrangements and the numbers
of particles are diverse the particle types are
diverse and then the crystal models you can see so
so the argument is that for these deep branching
nitrous puree you've got these hard aligned
particles shaped particles and and
you've got less complex more regular
uniform shaped in these later branching
particles but what you what you see is that
there's a general similarity in morphology in each
phylum and then variability within each strain
and so this is a this is a map of uh i forget
what is some statistical measure forget what
it is but anyway the point is you you're putting
the distributions of of measured uh crystals uh
and sure some of them are very similar but there's
the the argument is that there's sufficient
diversity uh and amongst different filer that
there's some hope i would argue that that at least
at phylum level and if you know what the what the
genes are telling you about what their function is
in the environment there's some hope of getting
a paleo environmental proxy from these things so
that's pretty exciting still a lot of work to be
done because the number of of strains for which
we have this level of information is 20 odd um
so still a lot a lot to do um then the question
is by geochemical cycling i i talked about them
swimming up and down field lines but really why um
and and the more species you look at you know and
do elemental maps this is a standard tem image and
then carbon oxygen phosphorus calcium magnesium
iron etc and then a color map of all of them
you can see the cell is carbon-based the the
iron uh from the magnetite is is there um but you
see all this other stuff here the polyphosphate
inclusions with calcium magnesium this guy's got
sulfur globules in the cell this guy's got poly
polyphosphates um in the cell so the question is
what what is all of that yeah and so
this is an idealized image um some some
um some strains have what are called ferrosomes
they're storing iron in in other forms apart
from uh magnesium or magnetite or grigorite uh
and and various other things within the cell
and there are other bacteria that that that
perform redox functions in in the water column and
sediments these are things called cable bacteria
which are very cool they're up to a couple of
centimeters long and their base is in the in the
in the sulfidic sediment and their top is in the
oxic sediment and they're they're facilitating
electron transfer transfer in redox reactions
um there are other giant sulfur bacteria that
that swim out of um nitrogenous into sulphatic and
and and back and forth these things are weird
they can swim at 60 times their body length per
second they're some of the fastest bugs going
um so so the these organisms are involved in
in redox chemistry in in in die genetic
environments so if you look at again
you're used to this by now these are the the
the different filer and different strains
if you look at at the gene content and the
metabolic pathways that that they're able to
to to follow the black circles indicate that they
have the genes for the full pathway so clearly
you'd expect them to be able to cycle iron and
and most of them you'd expect to cycle nitrogen
uh gray means they've got incomplete
pathways and and and white means absent
but but but the point is that that that
they've got the genetic content to be able
to be involved in biogeochemical cycling um i
mean humans have 98 of our genetic content is
has no function right so it could be that that
the genetic content is just there vestigially and
not playing a role but you know swimming
up and down magnetic fields across
a a redox boundary when you've got all of
this chemical equipment to make the most of it
it seems a bit far-fetched that they're not
doing that to me so the proposal has been made in
in these papers that that they're shuttling up
and down and being involved in sulfur oxidation
when they swim up nitrate accumulation within
the microoxide zone and then when they swim
down they're involved in sulfide oxidation
sulfite reduction nitrate reduction within
the anoxic zone and then the argument with
these different inclusions within the cell
that they're involved in the geological
sequestration not just of magnetosomal
magnetic particles but sulfur carbonate phosphate
etc so the really interesting thing will be to see
if eventually a budget can be produced to see how
significant mtb are in the global biogeochemical
cycling of elements um we just don't know but
it's an interesting question okay so i've gone
on long enough i'll i'll stop um i would argue
that the oia model for mtb is important but
overemphasized um and and i'd like to i'd like
to see us be a bit more sophisticated about that
um i'm probably whistling in the wind with that
because it's it's just so embedded a concept
i'd say mtb evolution really adds an
important dimension to understanding the
dynamo and and that's pretty cool
um they're incredibly diverse
but with that diversity it seems that each
phylum has distinct morphologies and each
species within a phylum has variations on
that morphotype so i think there's hope
for for developing paleo environmental proxies but
as i say you know you have to do this kind of work
for lots and lots and lots of living species in
order to infer back into the geological record so
that's work that's ongoing
lots to be done but that's a
that's a quick snapshot of some of the things
that that we gin fire and others and colleagues
have been thinking about over the last
few years and really enjoying so thanks
thanks very much andrew i think we can all um
give andrew a virtual round of applause for
a really interesting talk covering
a lot of different aspects of of mtb
um i can open the floor now to questions so if
anybody has a question you can uh raise your hand
um by a zoom or you can type it into the uh the
chat so we'll start with uh adrian much already
well uh thanks very much for the talk andrew
it's really really good i've i've learned a lot
i just have a question it's just more for sort of
looking at this from a paleomagnetic point of view
we often focus on mtb but my experience working
in the north sea there's an also an awful lot of
extracellular cellular by you know biogenic
magnetite as well um i'm just wondering if
we're focusing too much attention i mean mtp's
obviously there's all things we can do looking
at the evolution et cetera but for from a paleo
magnetic point of view we're focusing too much on
mtbs and not looking at other forms of biogenic
generation of magnetites or other magnetometers
agree 100 and and jinhua's in the audience still i
hope so this is something he and i've been talking
about and got some ideas about i i think the
reason we are where we are is because you know
of the beautiful crystallinity and stoichiometry
of the mtb so they're dead easy to spot
and the extracellular stuff's a lot trickier it's
it's quite diverse um i think it's really common
uh jinhua's actually got the evidence so so
that's something that we have to do i think
it's on his next on his agenda but i don't want
to speak for him i don't want to give too much
away but but totally agree really important and
you know ramon when he started his unmixing stuff
15 or so years ago um has has that d
plus e x detrital plus extracellular
component and i think extracellular is likely much
more common and important than we give a credit
we live in interesting times
there's lots more to be done yeah
so do we have any other questions for for andrew
yeah you should i might want to minimize the
paper that's on your screen andrew
and then we can hand over to to win
andrew yeah i i really enjoyed that learn
i thought i knew lots about magnetotactic
bacteria but obviously obviously not so that was
uh amazing and um most of this work uh actually
from my point of view seems non uh paleomagnetic
in a way because all the effort that needs to be
done is is in the biogeochemistry but is there
any hope do you think of identifying the sort of
major differences in species from a rock
magnetic or paleomagnetic point of view
oh there you get me onto a less optimistic note
um you're 100 right there's a lot of fundamental
microbiology genomics uh characterization work
and the magnetic characterization goes with it
um yeah there's so much overlap in magnetic
properties between different types um
that i i mean i i still think
you can tell biogenic magnetite
you know you were you were there for ramon's
talk at the santa fe meeting recently and and
um the complexity of of you know we're
used to thinking of single chained
bacteria and then once you get the multi-stranded
multi-chained uh looping back on itself chains
all those other geometries that are
producing non-central rich signatures
and forks and all the rest of it um well it's an
interesting time to characterize that stuff but
there's a lot more work to be done to do it and i
suspect we'll be in a big non-uniqueness situation
but we've got that anyway thanks
let's not kid ourselves we've got a big
non-uniqueness problem anyway oh yeah
for sure yeah the pathway to try and
somehow characterize in a broad sense the kind
of differences would be nice i mean you've got a
huge range in mythology of the of the magnetosomes
particularly the bullet ones you think would would
have less magnetic flux linkage to their neighbors
because you know they're going to a point rather
than flat surfaces that are interactive you might
as as like as complete magnetos megiditic bacteria
of course yeah you might think they also tend
to be aligned along 1-1-1 so it's the hard axis
so you need many many more of them to get the
same the same function yeah so that you know
and and they're in the oldest branching nitrous
puree dominantly so so it kind of makes sense
that that they didn't know what they were doing
then you know i don't know but yeah oh one more
question while you're here is it really true that
that martial meteor had magnitude because i i've
always told the students it's all crystallization
of uh magnetite on on the rim of carbon itself
did you miss the santa fe meeting where they
invited uh mr penny sleep sorry to talk she was
great and i was sitting next to richard harrison
and um she gave a lovely talk and very rigorous
very understated um you know characterizing
these particles and doing a fine scientific job
and i left like you unconvinced and richard
was chattering with excitement that was totally
convinced that there were magnetic fossils in
mars all right so it's still an open question yeah
all right thanks thanks very much and to have time
for another question for for andrew from anybody
if not i will i'll throw into you in terms of of
from a paleomagnetic perspective um what do you
think is the next sort of stage in understanding
um mtb contribution to to magnetic recording
in terms of next stage i'm not sure in terms
of rock magnetism i think distinguishing
vortex signals from super vortex signals is really
important and when you get flux closure structures
with magnetosome chain collapse those super
vortices become important um but i think super
vortices are really important in igneous rocks of
all sorts of descriptions too so i i think that's
a characterization issue that's challenged
to us um i think in terms of patio magnetism
you know magneto fossils are recording a lot of
signals that are really nice right they're ideal
single-domain particles so so there's nothing not
to like about them um and i think they're really
rather common where you have good records um for
me the biggest excitement is is trying to push it
back in time and get into the arcane and i've just
had a proposal declined on that so i'm a bit salty
so i want one uh last quick question
from from andre and then we'll um
wrap it up for this morning or this evening
uh you're you're on mute
andre can you un unmute andre
i'm sorry sorry greg always forgetting to do that
and it's great uh great talks thank you greg
for uh getting andrew uh to this audience
yeah and to be quick uh you know in in many
studies of bacterias in culture we know from
a lot of studies of bacterias and culture we know
that the magnetite degrades pretty fast even on
human time scales how how does it what mechanism
you see to for it to survive in essentially
just within the magnetite stoichiometry
in the geological type scale
really good question andre nice to
see you it's been a long time yeah
um um it's and it's great to see so many
friends that i haven't seen for a while um um so
you know if you go into pelagic carbonates
for example or or red clays in the north
pacific or south pacific like toshi yamazaki
studies you'll hardly see a vowel transition
but you'll see all of the signatures
of chains and single domain particles
and the strong uniaxial anisotropy so
that's probably severely mag hematized
but the basic magnetic properties are preserved
apart from the you know the vowel transition um
and and that's even in sediments that
have been oxidized for 800 million years
so it gives me hope that if and then the
question is you know how well preserved are
these signals what what mechanisms are keeping
them preserved some people would say that the
you know the organ the the
cell wall as it degrades
might be getting mineralized and i don't know
i find i i can't think of a mechanism that i
understand or that convinces me but that might
be protecting it from from the ravages of time
um but but you're right it's a good question and
i don't think people have done enough work on it
well just to continue sometimes we do see
world we still see where we transition in
let's say several tenths of million um
million years old samples so it's not
universal yeah but bacteria remember the weight
transition is seen easily in coarse materials
it's not grain size dependent it's just it's
the oxidation of the finer particles yeah i
agree i agree on that but okay you
you do see the difference in verb
in the record between uh mtbs and uh normal
data the detroit magnitude you can tell it
yeah so we published a paper in 2013 in jgr liao
chang was the first author where we looked at
low temperature results for pelagic carbonates
of all sorts of types and you got stuff with nova
where transition to stuff yeah yeah i agree
on that for you but it's not universal yeah
it's not universal yeah and neither should
you expect it to be because of oxidation yeah
yeah and maybe the the last uh stint on that i
can't recall if anybody tried to determine the
the cell cell light is perimetered from this
oxidized stuff using the high resolution
team parameter the lattice parameter for for the
for magnetite to make hemite crystals in there
okay can you see that they are going to the
maximized size side oh i'd have to ask gino but
yeah we tend to focus on the on the beautiful
stuff right the modern yeah right but well that's
but in the geological record when we've
done lattice fringes they've been magnetized
okay okay thank you very
much it was great to see you
same yeah cool thank you very much um so
i think we'll i'll draw the questions to
close but uh thank andrew again for uh
another uh fantastic presentation on mtb
so um before we bring the whole meeting to a close
just a few points of uh of schedule um so we have
another magnets meeting uh next week um which
is coming from gemma richardson from the british
geological survey and she's going to be talking
about space weather now the timing of that's
going to be a little bit later and it's going
to be at 9 00 a.m um british summer time um just
we're going to have a bit of flexibility
in the timing here to accommodate the
speakers um but we're always interested
in in more speakers so if anybody here
is interested in uh giving a presentation
for the magnet seminars or no of somebody
who would give a good presentation please
just drop myself or or or anything an email
um i should also say that for the the recordings
of these videos they are um uploaded um onto
earthref and they're given a cycle doi so
if andy has talked about something uh really
interesting today and you want to to use his
talk it will be given a doi so you can cite it
the videos are available to download there um and
um all the videos will be uploaded uh on to our
youtube channel as well so um for those of you who
have missed some of the early market seminars you
can get all the all the videos up there uh as well
and i just want to say um thank you to everybody
for um joining this week's magnets and i'll
hope to see you all next week cheers thanks greg